Did you know Spain is the country with
the strangest borders? On the map, it
looks like Spain has only two land
neighbors, France and Portugal. But in
reality, there are many more. Just the
border with France creates a few unusual
oddities. For example, the town of
Libya, which lies entirely within French
territory, only 2 km from the border,
but it is Spanish territory. This
phenomenon is called an enclave. And
moving further west, you'll find an even
more surprising case, pheasant island.
Long ago, Spain and France couldn't
agree on how to divide the island
because the border ran right through the
middle. So, they decided to take turns
owning it. For the first half of the
year, the island belongs to Spain, and
for the second half, the border shifts
and it becomes French territory. There
is also another neighbor hidden between
Spain and France, and Pandora. It's one
of the smallest countries in the world
with a population of about 80,000 and
almost half the size of New York City.
But Spain has another hidden neighbor,
and it's much larger, the United
Kingdom. Even though Britain lies far to
the north, it holds an overseas
territory at the very southern tip of
the Iberian Peninsula, Gibralar, which
for centuries has been a point of
dispute between Spain and the UK, as it
controls access to the Mediterranean
through the Straight of Gibralar. The
strait itself divides two continents,
Europe and Africa. But despite this,
Spain is the only European country that
shares a land border with Africa, thanks
to three Spanish enclaves bordering
Morocco, another unexpected neighbor.
Two of them are the cities of Suda and
Mala and the third is a tiny strip of
land that was once an island but over
time became connected to the mainland by
a narrow istmas creating the shortest
land border in the world just 85 m song.